All right everyone.
Hello and welcome to the opening
keynote session
for the Electronic Literature Conference
2026.
Unsupervised.
Thank you all very much for being here.
And greetings to those of you
who are joining by watching
the recording in the Stars repository
after this event.
We are really glad that you all are here,
and we especially want to
welcome Liliana von Bertram,
who's our presenter for today.
My name is Peter Edgar and I'm
the logistics chair for this conference.
And I'm going to introduce Liliana Von.
And with this bio.
William von Bertram is an African American
writer, poet, artist and educator
working at the intersection
of computation, AI, race, and gender.
Their practice engages
foundational questions
in contemporary poetics
and AI studies how algorithmic systems
encode and reproduce racial and gender
bias, how machine generated texts
troubles authorship and literary value,
and what critical and esthetic methods
might constitute a politics of resistance
within computational form.
They're the author of Travesty Generator
by Noemi Press,
a book of computational poetry longlisted
for the National Book Award in Poetry,
and which also won the Anna Rabinowitz
Prize and the Poetry Society of America.
Their other poetry collections
include Negative Money, Personal Silence,
How Minor, How Narrow, My
Escapes, A Slice from the Cake,
Made of Air,
and A Storm Is Blowing from Paradise.
Their chapbook A Black Story may contain
sensitive content, which I have here
with me, written in collaboration
with the large language model,
won the 2023 Diagram New Michigan Press
Chapbook Contest, and they're the coeditor
with Nick Montfort of Output and Anthology
of Computer Generated Texts, 1953 to 2023.
Bertram is a recipient
of the National Endowment for Arts Poetry
Fellowship, the 2024 Foundation
for Contemporary Arts Poetry Grant,
and the 2024 Deutsch Foundation
Rubies Grant.
They currently direct the MFA in Creative
Writing at the University of Maryland,
and serve as an affiliate faculty
in the Artificial Intelligence
Interdisciplinary Institute at Maryland.
And I'll say one more
that they edited this
Michigan Quarterly Review
special issue featuring many of you.
And I maintain a low grade
parasocial relationship
with the possum
that they collect pictures of.
So thank you so much.
Please
welcome warmly, Lillian von Bertram.
Oh, thank you so much.
That was wonderful.
Yes.
The possum.
We can talk about that another time.
But there is a possum, among other things.
Thank you so much, Petey.
Anastasia, everyone, for being here
and for inviting me.
I think ten years, I was like,
what is yellow?
How can I get there?
And would not have imagined
that I would one day be giving a keynote.
So I'm just really pleased
and humbled to be talking to
so many artists
and thinkers that I deeply admire.
I've taken the title of my talk
from Raymond
Roussel, who wrote a book called
how I Wrote Certain of My Books.
And this nod to
Roussel will become clear later.
But don't take it to mean that
I in any way feel comparable to her cell
or his level of eccentricity,
which I have yet to remotely approach,
and I think that's a good thing.
Our overlaps are few, but real methods
of constraint or procedure in writing,
and I find his title fitting
because I'm going to do some explanation
in response to a question
I was recently asked.
And to answer this question
does require some trips down memory lane
by memory lane.
And so I think you in advance
for your indulgence, some storytelling.
Recently,
a dear friend and writer
who I deeply respect timidly
made a confession after hearing parts
of this craft talk about my work.
They were slated to review my first book,
But A Storm Is Blowing
from Paradise
when it was published in 2012.
The review never happened,
they admitted, because after reading
the book, they realized
they did not know how to talk about it.
They had no quote frame of reference
for it.
In retrospect, they could have
just called me up and asked.
But now, looking through the arc
that I laid out,
it made more sense to them,
perhaps because I built its reference
points throughout my later work.
But first, the anecdote that leads
to the question and some ideas that
I'm considering as a writer with a wide
ranging and experimental practice.
This year, I attended the 2026
Association of Writers
and Writing Programs annual conference.
Think analog. Yellow.
Multiplied by 100 or 4000.
I usually skip this convening
out of cynicism for the whole supercharged
affair, but this year, the MFA program
that I direct was a conference sponsor,
and it took place only a couple miles
from my house, so I had to go.
The sponsorship afforded the program
a prime booth location at the front of the
conference book fair, and the book fair
is the real highlight of the conference.
And in recent years, at conferences
like AWP, MLA, HRO, and other university
symposia and conferences,
there's been an increase in panels
and talks about artificial intelligence.
I'm sure you've noticed this too.
While most of these use
the phrasing AI as the catch
all term aligned with popular conceptions
among laypersons,
what most actually talk about
are large language models or llms.
I'm reasonably confident
that I don't need to define
AI or llms for this audience,
so I'll skip over that.
And as an interested party, a writer who
has experimented with llms pre ChatGPT.
I looked forward to the panel
organized by the Authors Guild
and moderated by writer friend
Balcony Vara called Writers Resisting
AI despite their use of the catch
all term.
I knew they would be talking about Llms,
and I also had some idea
as to the posture of the panelists.
Given the blanket term,
AI was attached to resist.
If this linkage was designed
to pull in an audience, it worked.
The ballroom was standing room
only, packed
with an almost evangelical
resistance among attendees.
I was so in the air you could feel it.
One of the panelists was Alex
Hannah, coauthor
with Emily Bender of the excellent book
The AI Khan.
In it, Bender and Hannah offer
examples of everyday
individual acts of AI resistance,
such as simply not using
AI tools, turning off AI options,
and so on.
They also promote what Hannah in the panel
called ridicule as praxis.
In the book it is make fun of it
and troll the hell out of them.
Ridiculous practice was then
enthusiastically championed by another
panelist, highly regarded writer Carmen
Maria machado.
If a writer admits to using AI
by which they really mean llms,
or perhaps has even speculated of doing
so, ridicule them, shame them, and cancel
their contracts, as recently happened
with the book Shy Girl.
What the panelists didn't know
was that they had just given me
one way of interpreting an encounter
I had that very morning at 905.
As soon as the book fair opened,
I was approached by a woman
making a beeline for the booth
I was standing at.
She approached my university program table
and opened the conversation by stating
how much respect she had
for the institution
that is the University of Maryland
and his MFA program.
She held this respect right up
until she read my faculty bio
on the program website, and saw that
I had written a book with AI, but
she took to mean that I must be teaching
students to right use AI to write for her.
One necessarily must lead to the other.
She demanded to
know what I was doing
after seeing this in my bio.
She said she instantly lost all respect
for the program, and the school
clicked away and posted a nasty comment
on social media.
I didn't ask which one.
Shame on me was the message
for teaching students to write with AI.
I don't, by the way, in the panel
they did say to punch up
when doing ridicule not down,
which I interpret as not targeting
individuals so much as companies, brands,
institutions, organizations, etc.
as a sidebar, one can see how quickly
claims of AI can be weaponized
against already
marginalized writers by other writers
with real or imagined grievances.
Accusation can flow in the same direction
as power, which is why who is accusing?
Being accused may not be incidental.
But I do want to be fair to Bender
and Hannah's.
Our larger argument,
most of which I agree with
as a tactic
aimed upward at companies in AI hype.
It's a legitimate tactic
for legitimate target.
The trouble is, category drift.
When a tactic designed for corporations
doesn't stay aimed at corporations.
We can see how it can drift onto
individual writers and experiments,
and stops being about labor politics
and becomes more about esthetic or process
policing, i.e.
I feel your process is a legitimate.
Therefore, so is the work.
So just what do I think I am doing?
I have spent most of my writing life
being asked versions of this question,
often implicitly.
As a queer nonbinary person of color,
most of my personal life
has been spent
answering similar questions.
And so this type of spontaneous tribunal
has been more of a feature than a bug.
As a writer, I have resisted explaining
or over explaining my own work
out of a reluctance to commit the details
of an ever changing practice to paper.
But this question,
as it applies to writing, isn't new.
It's an old question
ask of experimental writers
and writing and a practitioners
of electronic literature.
Let me return to Russell for a moment,
lest you become your decoration.
His work was odd, unclassifiable, and
received with indifference or derision.
He struggled to find his public.
In 1911 1912,
he staged a theatrical production
of his novel Impressions of Africa,
to which the audience
is reported to have jeered and booed
a form of ridicule.
Yet in the audience
offering appreciation were Marcel
Duchamp, Apollinaire, and Francis Picabia.
Later admirers and defenders
included André Breton and Paul Éluard.
He was admired by the Surrealists,
and his mechanistic
style of composition
has been said to be proto,
and his work was later
rediscovered in the 1950s by the Oulipo.
While some recall, others do the reading,
Roussel answered the question as to
what he was doing from beyond the grave.
In the posthumous book
from which this talks title is taken,
Roussel may be more patterned than Edge
Case.
Gertrude Stein,
John Cage, Jackson Pollock,
and the Aleppo were dismissed as nonsense.
Not writing, not music,
not composition or plain parlor games.
Procedural practices of the past 100 years
have been met with similar demands,
accusations, questions, and yes, ridicule
is a computationally generated poem,
even a poem.
Is it?
Creativity is what you're doing
and how you're doing it.
Legible as writing,
let alone worth being called literature.
Note that ridiculous practice requires
no knowledge whatsoever
of the thing being ridiculed.
Ridicule, especially uninformed
ridicule, like a snap judgment,
is structured to prevent knowledge.
The moment you understand
a process of procedure,
it becomes harder to call it nonsense.
Doing the reading forfeits the pleasure
of outright dismissing the book,
and there is unearned pleasure and power
in the dismissal of the work of others.
But again, sometimes
difficulty is a failure of the writer.
I won't pretend it isn't, but other times
it is a condition of the work.
And I think of my friend and poet Douglas
Kearney.
Famously difficult.
His poems aren't digital poems,
but they wouldn't be possible
without digital tools.
Normative reading treats the difficult,
legible or unpredicted the same way
any normative system would as an error
or problem that needs to be collapsed
back into the nearest recognizable shape,
often a representative one.
I would argue that the writers I descend
from, including Kearney, and that some of
you may also descend from refuse
this type of collapse in norming.
We prefer a permutation space
that amplifies what a poem
or text can be, and how it can be made.
For me, this insistence emerges
from a core interest
that carries into my creative practice
that of systems interrogation,
going inside a system and using its logics
as the instruments of its explanation.
But I'm getting ahead of myself
into the argument before the explanation,
and before the language models
that led me to large language models.
As a young writer, I initially invested
a great deal in language's ability
to represent an express,
mostly mostly through metaphor.
Did this feel possible?
Over time, languages
limitations became apparent
when I tried and failed
at so-called accurate representation.
That's
because language is always symbolic.
One step removed, a just adequate
enough substitute for the real thing
that is embodied experience.
And as I pushed further into limitations,
I found myself drawn to the outer
edges of language to where can fracture
and buckle, be broken down and recombined.
But being drawn to the outer
edges of language
did not immediately have a method.
I was working on instinct.
My early poems were cryptic
stews of strange sound and sense,
and my peers and professors never knew
what the poems were going on about.
Sometimes I didn't either.
I did not know how to engineer the
fracture and intensity I was looking for
without sidestepping complete
semantic sense, and I may have an obscure
for obscurity sake.
I did, however,
have the good fortune of being fluent
in a language other than English Spanish,
which gave me access
to syntactical arrangements.
The patterns of Spanish
helped me break the patterns of English.
That I even got wind of how?
Computation language.
I think somebody has their microphone on.
Somebody.
But I even got
wind of how computation might interact
with language was by chance.
And given that I attended Carnegie Mellon
University, it was increasingly likely
as an undergraduate assistant
in the Human Computer
Interaction Institute, which
I never heard of until I was hired there.
It was one of several jobs
I held across campus.
My task was morphological markups
of Spanish words for a postdoc
who was building
automated machine translation software.
And in retrospect,
I may have been working on his startup.
I learned Spanish in grade in high school
and refined it while living abroad,
where study gave
way to the reality of language
being far more slippery and rebellious
when it came to the rules.
But it really doesn't work that way.
I often found myself
saying to the postdoc,
who didn't seem that interested
in the nuances he was,
after all, working towards
deployable commercial technology.
The machine needed to know something
about language, and I was teaching it
what I knew, which wasn't always the same
as what I felt about language.
The software relied on rules
without exceptions and was not designed to
handle language
other than strict utilitarian translation
and not contextual connections.
I was learning
what certain types of computation
could and could not do with language,
at least not yet.
But the project was interesting,
and I saw how computation might be
a pressure system for how I understood
and used language by forcing me to reckon
with my own approaches to the making
and breaking of language rules.
I finished marking up the word database,
and that was the end of my involvement
with the project, if not its ideas.
As a graduate student,
I was influenced by a lifelong fascination
with the cosmos, and through poetry,
I pondered the impacts of celestial
and gravitational forces
could have on bodies and language
could force be applied to language?
Did words have mass or heft?
Where do words exist in space?
This language travel along what waves?
If words could be marked up
and served in a program,
could words be multiplied squared, cubed?
A word times itself is what I was asking.
Nascent questions about permutations
and recombination.
Questions of math.
Multiplying words seemed possible enough.
But what did I know about rendering words,
much less
the relationships between words
mathematically or numerically?
Absolutely nothing.
But in one poem I multiplied consonants.
This poem appears in my first book,
but A Storm is Blowing from Paradise,
which treats Walter Benjamin Storm
interpretation of Paul
Please
Angelus Novus as a literally felt force.
It's called Queen City Fractal.
A whole world stacked in a garage,
a gauge, birds at the feeder, a gauge.
Someone walking
a buffalo beach on Christmas
waves way
beyond the pile of tremors of ice.
That person is married now. Done.
Thinking of the minute.
The sum of all birds at the feeder.
Bird plus two. Bird plus four. Bird
plus bird.
Better expressed as bird
plus one over two times bird.
And what did the savvy knight demand
but one penny for the first bird, two
for the second and four for the third.
He demands a single gauge.
Bosons, the carrier of forces
feather alone that flies.
He uses the feather to decorate
flight alone.
Requests only a strength carrier.
First birds one penny to the second, four
for three.
Celebrated as bird of a bird of a bird
to take as his reward.
That persona is whetted
now made to think minute.
Somebody that walks a buffalo beach
on Christmas.
Walks away of waves
beyond the accumulated vibrations of ice.
Enter
a worldly garage. Birds in the feeder.
Another meter that person marries. Now,
in addition to my basic attempt at word
math, you may sense an internal echo
within the poem.
Could language be a fractal and spiral
into and out of itself?
One way this poem probes
this possibility is through
the computational mechanisms
of machine translation.
The poem is broken apart
through iterations of translations,
and then reconstituted
as a funhouse mirror in its second half.
There are three fractal
like poems in this book, but the method
of putting pressure on and warping
language and narrative resurface strongly
in my second book, A slice from the cake
made of air
in a slice from the cake made of air.
I was inspired by what I could remember
of mathematical factorials.
I wondered how many permutations
existed of a word or poem if you took
n numbers of things are different ways,
like anagrams.
How many words can be produced by
a combination of a certain set of letters?
Now I am one of many in a
lineage of experimental
and computational composition practices.
Beat era poet and artist
Brian Gysin, with the help of friend
and computer scientist Ian Sommerville,
authored a series of permutation poems
in which the 4 or 5 word
title of the poem would be permuted
into some or all of its possible orders.
Some of these poems were among
the earliest examples of computer
generated poetry.
Sears permutation algorithms,
and of course on the screen,
is an example of one of Geisinger
best known permutation poems
that many of you, I'm sure have seen.
I am that I am.
Geisel is another writer
whose procedural approaches
surely engendered questions
about what he thought he was doing.
If this was writing, let alone poetry.
A slice from the Cake made of
air opens with the poem
sometimes I Asked to Be Bound.
This poem was subjected
to an iterative process of translation,
resulting in an English to English
translation that passed through numerous
intermediary languages.
Sometimes I asked to be bound,
but we never do it like that.
Why don't we ever do it like that?
After all, I ask for it from my father.
Anything I ask for, I get.
I say I am worth it
and we both know it's true.
We know there is a pattern.
The chimney and the rat's nest.
The leak always starts above.
I ask for me.
I want a mask.
The width of a rope, the sky
Mooney memories and the cut of them.
By this writing,
you'd think I wasn't born anywhere.
That I didn't,
however, briefly, carry a child.
Here comes the scything.
We know there is a pattern now.
The stinging.
Why can't we do it like that
with the taste
of mushrooms in the air?
Fragments of these iterations
wind throughout the book in sections
marked with repeated elements.
Our subscript zero, r,
subscript one, r subscript two, and so on.
Where our represents the number of items
being selected or arranged from a larger
set, an N is the total number
of distinct items available in the set.
I stand behind the fig leaf,
a lasso lashing rainstorm.
Kurita.
The traces of journeys that pass
as heaven under that place is heaven.
Firmness not composed.
Is heaven.
Colored is heaven. Without being able.
The star is many.
And scissoring.
Sometimes I ask to be bound
is reassembled from the fragments
into the closing poem, now
titled at intervals when the moon is blue,
I beg to be tried and trust.
Barring at any time.
Do we like that?
Like that in which always we like it
hindmost?
I buzz for it and whatever piece portion
shaped by canvas from Pie
Annex I utter I am a merit.
Together we appreciate what's bona fide.
Together
we fathom the lattice work in the lair,
in the flu,
the seepage alphas from there aloft.
For me, I charge.
I stand in need of a fig leaf
with the sweep of a lasso.
Heaven firmly their astral blah.
The snip of keepsakes aside this
what's been set down you'd consider
I hadn't been cherished.
That in any case, that in a nutshell
I failed a little darling within reach.
The rays breezes in we understand motif
presently a spot of taint.
We who can.
Why don't we make it where we love it?
On the wind with the bang of sugar?
It is and is not a different poem.
It is a new version of itself.
The math may have been applied
in precisely,
but the process nevertheless captures
something true and important.
A poem is not a fixed object,
but a probability space, a set of possible
arrangements
constrained and transformed by history,
by language, by the corpus
of what has already been written.
A poem that refuses to be a single poem
is not feeling resolution,
just declining it.
Fast forward a few years,
and it was through Nick Montfort's work
and other writers that I was exposed
to the possibility that I could write
computer code to do permutations
in random chance operations using Python.
I learned some Python
through the roboticists
at my local makerspace,
and with their assistance,
I was able to bring to life
a project that had been brewing in my mind
for some time
a randomized poem generator
that took my own corpus as a data
set and generated random collaged poems
at the press of a button
powered by a Python controlled Raspberry
Pi microcontroller.
And I'll add some of the stuff
that's coming up on the screen.
That receipt printer is also like
anagrams.
Randomized poem generator
that took my own corpus as a data
set and generated random collage poems.
The press of a button powered by a Python
controlled Raspberry Pi microcontroller.
These poems were simultaneously generated
and printed out on a
thin strip of paper
from a small receipt printer.
Finally, my abstract
interest in permutation
and randomization
became embodied and literal.
Like the machine translation experiments,
input transformed through a system
to make output that carried traces of
the original alongside its transformation.
Computation
offered another avenue to rupture
normative syntax and release intuitive
and associative connections in language.
A question I have asked myself is why
non-normative experimental composition
and permutation felt less
like an adopted poetic technique
than a recognizable way of being.
To answer this, I must reach
even further back in personal history,
and I want to frame this carefully
as the experience of at AWP,
which was about a book and the job I do.
It's not the same as this experience
of being policed for one's identities.
They aren't
the same stakes for the same harms.
And I don't bring this up
to suggest equivalence, but to show how
instruction in the enforcement
of legibility is intertwined
with the origin story of my poetics,
which is one that resists binaries.
During a collage making activity
in seventh grade art class,
I glued on a magazine picture of two girls
kissing as a baby queer.
I was drawn to it not for its shock value,
but for its triumphant inclusion
in a mainstream magazine.
This inclusion
drew the attention of a clique of girls
sexuality private investigators.
They took one look at my collage
and demanded to know, are you a dike?
Having no idea what that was,
I said as much.
I was like 12.
Even today, I can see the way her head
and neck moved sharply from side to side
as she crossed her arms and said,
you know, a butch.
Still no recognition, a lesbian.
Despite the
red hot flush over my face,
I stammered out a rebuttal
that got them to back down,
conceding with a scoff.
Okay, we just wanted to be sure
they put me back in, checked,
and I covered the women's faces
with a picture of a piano.
The word and the fluency stayed with me,
as did the way these girls
did the work of the normative system
by patrolling its borders
and enforcing its edge, probably more
for their own sense of identity than mine.
Having never been in
especially narrative writer
and preferring anesthetics of fragment
and association,
I finally produced,
with the aid of a graphic designer,
visual poems in a series
called World Maps to represent
and express these jarring moments
of selfhood punctuated equilibrium.
These poems, like the one on the screen,
appear in Negative Money,
A Book of esthetic Mixtures
and a significant departure
from my previous book, Travesty Generator.
But the education of these girls
produced in me was not only a grievance,
but a set of habits
that influenced my poetics.
I learned how legibility gets enforced
and grew suspicious of demands
that a thing or person
explain itself into a simpler thing,
that it looks like what is expected.
That same year,
I turned in a poem to class.
That was a drawing of a stop sign.
The teacher was not amused.
I developed a tolerance for being unread
or difficult to read,
that was best expressed in the poem
as concrete visual object in world maps.
I landed on visual representation to enact
what felt like a truer poetics
of the fragment of visual fragmentation
that I had experimented with before.
The book
Travesty Generator, published in 2019,
about three years
after I started exploring
computer programing and textual
with Python as a literary artifact, marks
a moment of culmination
and trajectory shift in my practices.
It began after the first election of Trump
and the increase in anti-Black violence
and police brutality, conditions
that very much mimicked conditions of old.
It's not that I had been writing
about questions of race and discrimination
in previous books,
but this commentary was opaque
and often obscured in the language
and forms that operated on the level of
if you can recognize it,
you'll recognize it.
And I've always been called to write
about race and discrimination
as they're intersectional,
with an inseparable
from my other identities
related to gender and sexuality.
I wanted to write more directly into this
period of renewed racist violence,
but through my static lens,
and proved myself, at the very least,
that computational methods could
and should be used to respond
to the brutality of the moment,
and that it could move
from fringe interest
to necessary interrogative strategy.
After all, it is these technologies,
from redlining to flat camera surveillance
to credit scores that digitally encode
anti-Blackness into our social codes.
Racism is a technology with purpose built
algorithms.
Travesty generator uses code to explore
historical and personal instances
of otherwise encoded
anti-Black racism and resistance.
This is systems interrogation
in a literal form.
If racism runs on code,
then I could go inside code
and turn its logic back on itself
to reveal its workings.
The poem as counter program.
As I began this work, programing in Python
using physical hardware
like Raspberry Pi, I heard many things
in response, often negative.
And perhaps some of you have heard
the same things.
I was helping to usher in robots, taking
over everything and eliminating our jobs.
Me as a single person responsible
for all of that.
That there was no craft
in pressing a button and presto change.
Oh, you got a poem
with no thought or agency at all.
It made poetry too easy.
Too much like cheating.
Not enough suffering for the art.
What did I think I was doing?
On the surface,
it looked like pressing a button.
Cheated through the work
of writing a poem.
But in practice,
as some of you well know, and
especially if you don't have
substantial fluency in programing,
it is far more time
consuming and difficult to craft a program
that generates a poem and using language
dictionaries that you compile yourself.
It would have been much easier for me
to just observe the observable world
and write a poem about the observation,
using
whatever language was within my reach,
and occurred to me first.
Programs do what they're directed
to do with words they're directed to use.
This means first you must choose the words
the n total number of distinct items,
and in the set the program selects from.
These ought to be words you want to read,
which means first you must read.
Every step is an agent. Authorial choice.
Travesty generator is a
deliberately black
and deliberately computational project
where the poem's forms
were also interpretive content,
and so is a black story
may contain sensitive content.
The book written with a large language
model.
Now, I did not explain all of this history
to the woman confronting me at the book
fair table.
She seemed to have an impassioned
monologue queued up, ready to defend
creative creativity in writing
from the soul sucking robotic apologists
like myself who are teaching students
to write with AI.
If she was most upset about the book, a
black story may contain sensitive content.
She could have read its introduction,
which characterizes it as a critical
and creative research experiment
and counter demonstration, a term borrowed
from Algorithmic Justice League founder
Joy Winnie of Large Language Models,
one that uses the models
to reveal their biases and hallucinations.
She would have learned
that this experiment uses comparison
as an assessment of early standard
GPT models, with a model inflicted
by a black author, Wendell and Brooks,
we Real Cool, as Brooks's
most anthologized poem, sometimes to her
chagrin, is certainly part
of the original training data and likely
several of her other books as well.
But the model required further
tuning to point it
towards the patterns of her voice.
A word on this Brooks's work
and the Brooks model function
here as a contrast or antithesis,
not as substitute.
The use here is intended
to be interpretive rather than extractive
for research purposes, not generally use.
The point was to show
what the generic model could not do
or reach without this framing.
One premise of the work
is that computational systems,
including narrative ones,
are cultural systems,
and the surface text of Llms
can be interpreted through this lens.
In the book, I probe generic GPT models
and the inflected model
with the same prompt
tell me a black story.
The generic model responds similarly
in repeated attempts, demonstrating
that the model had a rather limited
perception of what a narrative story is.
Granted, this is in like 2021 2022.
It has changed since then, so
the outputs followed a typical once
upon a time format with rising action,
conflict, climax, conclusion.
The stories about black
people were all hard luck, discrimination
and racial uplift stories.
Following the typical story structure,
one even implied that slaveholders
that taught slaves to read
and write were kind people.
Now, the stories from the inflected
model were far more personal and joyful,
more first person reflection
than flat toned, omniscient narrator.
This was also systems interrogation,
going inside a system
and using its own logic
as the instrument of its examination.
This was still during
the time when people were amazed
at what language models could do.
When there were clickbait headlines
like an AI wrote this article, and so on.
Everyone was exclaiming, either
with trepidation or optimism, how scary
good models were at generating
flawless text.
A flawless text doesn't mean coherence,
comprehension, or cultural competency.
The implicit thesis of the project is
that while language models are interesting
and compelling in some respects, there's
no evidence that they should be trusted
with anything even close
to creative or cultural competency.
Yes, the book is written with AI,
and that using a language
model was necessary to demonstrate
not just potential, but
the very problematic inherent failures
that she inquired about the book.
She may have learned that this project
did not use GPT as we know it today,
and that the process
of querying the model from the back end
was itself a language
exploration through corpus building.
What I wish I had said is
that I arrived at large language models,
the way I have arrived at language models
throughout my practice,
not as convert or resister,
but as interrogator.
It began
with the Spanish morphology at HCI
than machine translation and permutations,
Python powered stochastic generation,
natural language processing,
and then transformer architecture
all along the way,
pushing on the materiality of language
and the tolerances
of what a poem could hold.
This history helps explain why
some of the two most available postures
don't really fit me,
not the uncritical embrace
she and other writers have imagined,
and not the reflexive refusal
the panel was selling down the hall.
Interrogation,
I hope, can be a third stance.
If she had done again
even a cursory amount of research,
she may have learned that
in the classroom.
I teach the long, colorful and dynamic
history of computational narrative systems
and the poets, artists, writers,
and researchers that have built and used
these systems to explore the mysteries
of language, linguistics, and
and what is but a normalized, agreed upon
schema of borders and boundaries
that, when put under pressure,
expands the possibilities for being.
And contrary to
her belief, I do not teach
writing students how to write with AI.
They don't need to be taught that at all.
They already right alongside machine
learning models when they select
predictive text option in their text
messages, emails, word processing
programs.
What I do teach is what I call
intellectual self-defense
knowledge about what a language model
really is, what it can and cannot do,
where it came from, how it is
made, its biases and limitations.
Rather than snap judgments, students
look critically at how artists and writers
have engaged
these models as a medium
in their own right,
not as slop replacements
for writing or creativity, but as modes of
exploring the relationships
between computation and language
and what computation can reveal
about language.
Of course, the acronym
AI has swelled into a term
that is applied to so much that
it means everything or nearly nothing.
When the woman saw AI,
she was not reacting to technology so much
as a term that is eaten technologies
and now functions almost like a feeling.
Part of intellectual self-defense
is refusing that collapse
too, by
insisting on the specifics of the system.
If she had arrived at the conversation,
which she thanked me for
with informed questions instead of snap
judgments based on assumptions,
maybe the posture would have been less
accusatory, but maybe not.
And I get it.
These judgments, especially about AI,
can serve a useful purpose for some
who find themselves overwhelmed
with information and competing arguments.
A snap judgment can give you something
to immediately
stand for or against,
which can be expedient.
If this mental efficiency
has the same downsides as AI efficiency,
sidestepping your own process
of critical thinking and reasoning,
this demand at my
booth is an operation
that most procedural, procedural,
experimental, and Ellet writers
have probably faced repeatedly.
That operation is confronting
and unpredicted or unimagined arrangement,
and responding with pressure
to collapse it back into something
recognizable and reducible,
or to dismiss it entirely.
Ridiculous.
Praxis requires
refining fixed categories, real writing
or not with AI or against AI,
creativity or slap.
Electronic and experimental literature
do not resolve into something simpler.
Nor treat eligibility and difficulty
as problems to be solved,
but as necessary conditions of the work.
There is a danger that ridicules praxis
for closes on practice
and shrouds a lineage
that must be rediscovered decades later.
The departed Roussel, waiting until the
1950s for his resurrection by the Oulipo.
What is a praxis that narrows the space,
the permutation
space, of what writing and literature
is permitted to become?
So I explained
what I could in the short amount of time
I had with this woman, and she did respond
positively, exclaiming
that it was impossible for anyone
to know all of this from a website bio
that mentions AI.
True, but is my faculty
bio really the place for this argument?
Maybe it is when I casually suggested
that this could have been averted
if she had done a little research.
She doubled down, insisting that
as soon as she sees AI, she sees red,
and no way was that going to inspire her
to do more research.
This is her choice.
She offered three more things.
First, a tip.
I should change my bio
to be more explanatory, or to say
something else that other people don't
get the wrong impression.
The second she would amend her
nasty social media post.
And third, before she continued her way
around the book fair,
she showed me her own books
and handed me her card and a small tangram
puzzle set with her face
sticker on the packaging.
I have fond childhood memories
of being stymied by these.
The Tangram puzzle is a Chinese geometric
dissection
puzzle
consisting of seven flat geometric pieces,
a square, some triangles, a parallelogram
arranged initially in a square.
The game is to rearrange
the pieces into different flat shapes,
like a duck or a house,
without overlapping any pieces
for the willing investigator
and number of pieces in a set.
Taken are different ways
can produce countless fascinating shapes.
Thank you.
That's all I've got.
I'll stop sharing.
Thank you so much, Lilian.
Yvonne.
And in solidarity,
I've joined you on my porch as well.
This one needed some sun time.
And if there are any questions
in the audience,
I'd love to open both the chat.
And if you want to raise your hand
to ask any questions,
we can open the Q&A portion now.
Thank you so much.
That was an incredible great talk.
Thank you.
Part of what got me really excited.
I had to grab a piece of scrap paper
and a Sharpie as you were speaking.
Is that so many of the pieces
of your story hint at just sort of the
maybe some of the reality
that we experienced that a hidden
but not secret language like underlies
and animates the world of the poems
and like in the world of the world,
like math code differences
between languages that we translate
to the normative in general.
Like, I'm just wondering
what sort of programs you're
writing now and what sort of programs
you want to see more of
right now.
I am,
so I'm working on
like a, like a piece of hardware
that can sort of
give me data from the plants in my garden.
Using Raspberry Pi,
because I have a garden.
I'm doing also like a lot of sort of like
local data.
This is
this is behind the possum, by the way.
So there's a possum.
Like everyone's
just going to have to like,
you know, agree that there's a
there's a possum happening.
I'm collecting a lot of local data
in my like immediate space.
And so I have a ton of this visual data
and audio data.
A lot of it is possible and other things.
And so computationally
I'm working on like how to process
how to process that,
sort of like what to do with it.
So that's taking me
in a lot of different directions,
like thinking about things
like image captioning, image recognition,
you know, what kinds of models
and things can be built from scratch
to like, deal with, deal with this data.
But it's all extremely hyperlocal.
It's like literally
it's like outside my window.
So yeah,
that's sort of what I'm working on now
as far as computation is concerned.
Awesome.
We have a question for Mark sample
that asks there's
ridiculous practice practice.
And then there's facile misrepresentation
as critique.
I'm thinking of Joe Lipa's recent
New Yorker article and would love to hear
you risks on a response if you have one.
Yeah, I thought I,
I, I wrote I wrote a letter to the editor
actually about that
which didn't get published,
which doesn't surprise me.
Yeah.
I thought like I her
I think she mischaracterized the history
of computationally generated literature
in text as the prehistory of slop.
I don't think that's right.
I think that that just kind of like misses
that.
Mrs.. Mrs..
A bit.
Right.
That's not that's not what was happening.
And so
I just sort of think that's wrong,
but it's also it's really convenient
at the same time.
Like of course there's been this like,
you know,
we have slop today
because of this other thing.
And I don't exactly think that's true.
Oh, someone's asking more context
about Laporte's argument.
Yeah.
So Laporte
kind of goes into like we have AI slop,
a lot of generated text right now,
but that there has
been, you know, a history
of computationally generated text.
And she cites output as.
Sites output,
the anthology of computer generated text
as something
as a, as a text that's like usefully doing
that work or providing that history.
So she speaks favorably about it.
But I think characterizing that as like
the prehistory of slop is wrong.
So I did I can pull up maybe like what
I what
did I like post on Instagram or something
like my my letter to the editor.
It's there.
Yeah, I think it was when I looked at
it was behind the paywall,
but it is available from the New Yorker.
She's a critic at large.
Dina asks, how do you explain to someone
the bias involved
in generating language
from particular databases?
As involved in generating language?
Yeah.
I assume you're you're talking about
or asking about
the sort of initial training of the model
and that like those,
I guess I could explain to me how I would
how I talk about it to my students,
which is
that like when you're when you're taking,
you know, like like data
is data is not neutral and data
is compiled by humans and humans choose
where they get that data from.
And so if we're getting textual data
from a corpus of books
that have been digitized
then already, right,
we have a bias that is, you know, towards
digitized text, right?
So it's not neutral.
It's not representative of, like, all the
texts in history or anything like that.
And it's also just text, right?
There's more to language than just text.
And there's more to writing,
I think, than just than just text.
So, you know, and also like, who has
funded, you know, building that database.
What were their initial ideas around it?
How old is it?
How recent is it. Right.
Is it licensed? Is it stolen data. Right.
All of these things, it's sort of like,
you know, I describe it as building
a house on a crooked foundation,
like everything inside of the house.
Like, if it's all you know,
I can always tilt my frame to make it all
look even, you know, inside the house,
even if it's, you know,
built on this frickin foundation.
But the foundation is still,
you know, pretty problematic.
It's like,
you know, it's like it was still built
on a Superfund site kind of thing.
And that, like,
that's the bias is baked in.
Right?
And and it always is,
like with lots of things.
Right.
That bias is baked in.
And that helps explain it to, to students
and also people who are encountering
language models as AI as like this is AI
sort of like out in the wild, right?
Without where the origins of the language
model has been totally obscured.
And that's, you know, of course,
very useful for the tech companies.
And Bender and Hannah do a good job
of talking about this obscurity.
And so, do you know, sort of a
lot of a lot of other folks.
Trying to keep up with here.
Are you going to release
the model of plans for writing data?
If I, if I finish it, if I ever, like,
get it to get it to work?
Yes. The Eliza project.
Yes. We are trained from human. Yes, yes.
No, I don't think.
No, there's
I don't think we can expect bias free AI.
I don't think that's.
I don't think that's possible.
Like you said,
stepping out, like stepping out of one
bias is stepping into another.
I'm wondering the way that that might,
like, parallel
into the sorts of questions
about workshop like that.
All of your writers
are bringing their themselves
into the workshop,
and they're bringing their eyes to work.
That was written from one eye.
Unless they're writing collaboratively
or writing with computers like that
just seems that there's
there's a lot of ways in which
all of the questions
about even appropriation,
like play play into that,
based on my reading of a black spray,
may contain sensitive content is like,
where do we get these ideas and stories
and rhetorics from?
It's from preexisting things.
But how does that play out
pedagogically,
when you're discussing with your students?
It does depend on the
class in like a poetry workshop.
It's a really different environment,
and the stakes are different
for like graduate students
in creative writing
than for a class of specifically about,
you know,
algorithmic writing and literature
and examining models and teaching them.
So a class I taught and we'll
teach again called Computers
Killed the Creative Writing Star.
Like really goes into that, right?
So students came into that
and I and I believe they will continue to
come into that with a lot of skepticism,
not so much around like computation
and computational models,
but around AI as language models.
So they approach it.
My experience has been they approach it
with a lot of skepticism and fear,
but also that partly has to do
with what information is available
about their origins.
Right?
Because obscuring the origins
and the reality of all the labor.
Right.
There is no cloud behind
that is part of the tactics of AI hype.
And in workshops like students in sort of
a if like bog standard creative writing
workshop, students are coming to that
with different expectations and very much
want nothing to do with language models
unless they do.
Right.
Unless that's part of like
the inquiry of their practice.
Right? Do
a student's are interested in computation?
So the stakes are different
and we set that up.
But I think there is a recognition of sort
of like what we bring to a workshop,
you know, like we bring stuff with us
all the time.
We don't we don't just like we don't show
up, as you know, sprung from Zeus's head
or anything.
But all of those things influence
like our position.
Right.
Like from where,
where we standing socially. Right.
In order to reply and look at and critique
and think about work
and all those things are part of
what makes the workshop
a very complicated, contested,
but also very productive space.
I don't know if that answers
your question. Thank you.
Yes. Copy.
Yeah.
I'm struck by the
tension you bring up with the tension
I feel, too, between
interest in computational writing
and avant garde
poetic practices,
especially those with relation to math
and technology as a space of beauty
and artistic innovation
and and even sort of humanist exploration.
And then the.
Part
that is involved in the critical work
or the political contestation
of these systems.
And if I heard in your talk
both a beautiful articulation
of how that congealed
in your poetic practice,
but then the specter of vulgar critique
against the systems
that demand them right,
in that it is
these same systems that we make art with
that are used to troll syllabi
for well-funded troll outfits.
I mean, they don't, but I think it's
helpful to narrate it a little bit, right?
We don't know. The senses are.
So I'm not expecting you to respond
to these particularities, but improvements
to the sophistication of metaphor,
recognition and generation determine
how well Palantir products
identify dissidents to be disappeared
or find people and fields
to target with weapons, things like this.
And so in that tension.
Sometimes I feel like the best thing
I can hope for, for
my poetic practice, is to like,
wait ten years and then come back to it.
But but that's that's cowardly too.
And you point to some of the ways that our
and our community
points to the ways that,
a non Manichean,
non simplifying vulgar critique can,
could
be more effective
perhaps or open other avenues out.
So sorry.
That's, that's a longish comment,
but I do want to put it on the table.
And the question there is sort of
whether you reject or sort of
as, as understanding
where the reflexive AI stuff
comes out of and working as an artist,
not a political scientist.
Why do we fight for nuance
now and how make it useful?
That's a huge question.
Why fight for nuance now?
I mean,
part part of me from like,
a very sort of like human place feels like
nuances, nuances
like why I even exist as a person.
Like, so it feels like
imperative,
you know, in some ways to do that.
Like,
almost like can't help it in some ways.
But I also think, like part of
what's gone on,
especially with like
AI is like the work of these companies,
what they have done to flatten
what they do
into something that is like, that obscures
what it's actually doing.
And like that,
I think is really problematic
because it is actually doing
like a lot of very harmful things. Right?
That gets like dressed up
as something else. Right?
Like universal good and all this other
kind of like crazy stuff.
And they're working really hard at that.
And so, you know, especially like,
you know, as a, as an educator, it's like
my job is to kind of try and tease
those things out, right?
For myself and also for students. Right?
So we're more equipped to kind of like
make our own decisions.
Right?
How people choose to respond
is really up to them.
Right?
I have known people are going to respond
and do what it is
that they're going to do.
And I do think there's
there's room for all.
I like to say that there's room
for all kinds.
It takes all kinds in this work
that we're doing.
But yeah, arguing for nuance,
like because it's all it's all nuance.
There's some stuff isn't.
But like a lot of it is nuance.
I don't think that really answers
your question, but I was trying to hit
hit a hit a bunch of things there.
Caitlin says.
I love the talk and hearing
how your personal histories and artistic
journey are woven into the moment.
It also reminds me of how experiments from
the margins are so often the first
silence, or the first to self-censor.
The AI and experimental writing
controversies remind me a bit of the porn
and censorship,
and closing down to the feminist
small presses
trying to imagine the content
and sexual politics.
Not that everyone stopped experimenting,
but the impulse to self check around
creating that work was strong.
But we lose when artists,
especially artists at the margins,
are the first to shut down
Love Illit artist experimenting.
Thank you so much
for sharing your practice.
And Michael has a question.
Do you think AI assisted creative
writing is starting
to have best practices for workflows,
or is it still too early days
with various models competing from
the frontiers and open weight offerings?
I, I don't know,
because I, I don't
I don't do AI assisted creative writing.
So that's, that's that's not what I,
you know, when I use language models, it's
not what I use them for.
So I can't I can't really say.
I mean, if, if people are creating
best practices and workflows
for themselves, that's probably true.
I do think,
but I do think like I am sort of among
a group of writers and people
who are thinking a lot
about open weight and open source systems
and what it means to create
community centered language models like by
and for writers and artists.
So I think that's one place
where that's getting really interesting,
and that's something that I would like
to see almost like kind of like
kind of like a makerspace for, but
with, with language model architecture.
Right?
I think language
model architecture is very interesting.
Right.
And sort of like building your own, you
know, kind of thing is very interesting.
So I think like there's possibility there,
but I don't really know
what other writers are necessarily doing
in terms of their workflows or practices.
I know in a in Negative Money,
you have a couple of poems
that are almost written back against AI
where you say,
when I ask the AI a certain question
or about a certain thing,
and that is different
than what you did in a black story,
may contain sensitive content.
Those poems predate
actually predate a black story,
and they predate a black story by years
in that
they were originally they were written
with talked to transformer.
If any of you and you remember that
website from like 2018 or something,
which was that
that early way of exploring GPT.
And so that was like
that sort of like back and forth
with the model before I really before
I knew what it was doing
and how it was doing, what it was doing.
That was like very early experimentation.
And also that was like
pre guardrail, right.
Where would you know where it would
sort of like it would go
off the chain
with lots of its responses, which
I found interesting and
more nuanced because it was really just
it was kind of bizarre.
And then when I started accessing
GPT from the back end
and running models locally, it was sort of
like anything could happen, right?
But that was kind of part of the interest
of like working with them in
like computationally interesting, right?
Working with them as opposed to what
we're kind of using now.
I want to open the floor to maybe one
final question.
We're coming down to our time here,
I believe.
I'll read what coffee said.
Part of what I struggle with
is the prehistory of technical,
avant garde poetics, like Gabriel
D'Annunzio and Filippo Marinetti,
are central
reference points for AI industry leaders
like Peter Thiel and Marc Andreessen
explicitly enthusiastic
about Italy fascism on the left.
Some prefer the avant garde politics
of the Bavarian Soviet Republic.
It's not clear to me
how we get one, but not the other.
Yeah,
yeah, it's I mean, people
are going to pick and choose, right?
Like what's you can always you can always
find something that's going to support,
you know, if you want fascism,
you're going to find
you're
going to find somebody to support it.
You are and there's there's nothing
I feel there's nothing, nothing I can do
about, you know, people
who are choosing to see it
and use it that way.
I don't know that we can have one
without the other,
but but they're definitely
has to be the other, right?
Which is this nuance that I think.
For me, that's a space.
That's a space that I think is
that is like the space of exploration.
Right? That is sort of like what?
Otherwise there's just there's
no discussion. Right?
It's one or the other. Right.
And if only I don't know anything.
That's that, that's well, a few things
are that simple, but, I think that it is
that it's put as only one
or the other is by design and is not real.
Right.
Well, it does bring to mind the importance
of continuing to do the work
because another will do their work.
And so continuing to do this work,
something that I feel really grateful
for. Your talk and thank you for
for fielding these questions.
And could everyone
please give another round of applause
to Liliana von Bertram
for this wonderful keynote?
Thank you all so much.
Stupendous. Thank you.